A Guide to the Henry Hotze Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #11236
Henry Hotze Papers ca. 1834-1887
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
11236
15 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This material was given to the Library by the National Geographic Society of Washington, D. C. through its Library Director, Susan Fifer Canby, on May 9, 1996.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 15 items, ca. 1861-1866 and 1959-1972, pertaining to Henry Hotze(1834-1887), Confederate propagandist. The writings chiefly concern Hotze's views on the conflict between the North and the South, particularly the effects on the Confederate states, and also contain views on the Mexican Expedition.
Container Listing
- Papers of Henry Hotze
  - "Some Arguments in Favor of Confederate Independence":, ca. 1861; AL, 25 p.
    Draft of a letter to P. Hamber, London.
  - "Anniversary of Washington's Birthday":, ca. 1862; AL, 7 p.
    Draft of a letter to "Messrs. Editors" from "One of your Readers." Re the conflict between the North and the South
  - Letter to the Right Honorable Lord Campbell (Lord Strateheden), London., 1863 Jan 24; AL, 22 p.
    Re the conflict between the North and the South and British involvement. Draft.
  - "Les Principes de la Colonization par rapport a la Question Mexicaine":, ca. 1863-1866; AMs, 47 p.
    Draft of Mexican Pamphlet. Includes additional section II in another hand. Re the Mexican Expedition, 1861-1867.
  - Letter to the Editor of the New York Herald., 1865 Jan 24; AL, 6 p.
    From Paris. Draft. Re the conflict between the North and the South and French involvement.
- Research Material
  - "Henry Hotze, Confederate Propagandist" by Charles P. Cullop:, 1959, 1972; Thesis (electrostatic copy)
    Presented to the Corcoran Department of History, University of Virginia. Related letter, May 12, 1972, from the National Geographic Society to the University of Virginia Library requesting a copy.
  - "Rebel Propagandist: Henry Hotze" in Nine Men in Gray by Charles L. Dufour., 1963; Printed (electrostatic copy)
  - Research Material re Henry Hotze and William Parker Snow., 1963-1972; 8 items (two electrostatic copies)
    Includes: Typed manuscript, May 11, 1972, concerning the unsigned letters and manuscripts obtained by General Greely from William Parker Snow; Copies or transcripts of catalog cards and biographical information pertaining to Henry Hotze and William Parker Snow
    Guide to the Archives of the Government of the Confederate States of America
    by Henry Putney Beers notating entries on Henry Hotze and Colin J. McRae.